Um, it does take a minute for everybody
to start, but the recording has begun.
Um, and again, for those who are just
joining, uh, it takes a minute for all
of the people to get moved in from the
waiting room. So, we're just giving it a
minute on there. And in the meantime,
I'll just introduce myself, uh, Dominic
Serlo with the New Mexico Department of
Health. We are here to help uh the
department of health staff are here to
help facilitate this from an
administrative standpoint. Um and then
the chair is Chris Pascus who is here.
And Chris, I'll turn it on over to you.
>> Hello everybody. Hopefully you all know
me by now. Um I'm Chris Piscus. I'm the
chair of this board and I'm on the
advisory board and um I'm a veteran and
I'm holding that role in this uh I'm
[clears throat] the veteran
representation on the advisory board. Uh
and I'm also an ambassador for the Royal
Karts project and I've got
a great relationship with the medicine
I've been working with for about three
years now um in this in a therapeutic
capacity. Um, and before that I
used it in a recreational capacity. And
so,
um, I'd like to start these meetings off
with just a a short 30 seconds of,
um, silence to kind of acknowledge all
the chaos in the world and all the
suffering going on in our communities,
throughout our state, throughout our
country, and throughout the world. Um,
and
the purpose of this is really just to
um
to hold a a little bit of space and
create a small container of calm and a
and world for chaos. So, just 30
seconds.
All right, thank you all. Um, next up, I
would uh
like to um have everybody go ahead and
introduce themselves. Um, I want to
remind everybody that we passed the
bylaws last time and if you do not
introduce yourselves and we end up
voting on a proposal or something like
that today. Um, you will not be able to
to do that. So, please make sure to
introduce yourselves and uh if you want
to have a a say in how this all shakes
out,
>> just to let everyone know if they wish
to speak uh please raise your hand as I
don't believe. Fantastic. Thank you.
Yeah. And I'll I'll mute you. Uh, first
we have Eric Bucker. I will uh allow
your mic
please. Eric, when ready, unmute
yourself and begin.
>> Hello, my name is Eric Baka and I'm
joining the committee for the second
time I think it is. And I just wanted to
um introduce myself and tell everyone
hi.
>> Good night.
>> Thank you very much.
>> Pause for one second. I forgot to ask
for one other thing. Please uh while
you're introducing yourself, um let us
know if you're from New Mexico and what
what affiliations you have. So,
>> okay. Yeah. Uh I'm from New Mexico and I
don't have any affiliations with uh any
companies or uh mushrooms or anything
like that. So,
>> thank you very much, Eric. Next, we have
Estan. I have allowed your mic. Please
unmute and speak when ready.
>> Good afternoon everybody. Uh Chris,
thank you again for hosting today. My
name is Steon Hernandez. Uh I am a New
Mexico resident, owner of New Mexico
Fungi, a currently gourmet mushroom farm
based out of Albuquerque and I am also
the president of the New Mexico
Micological Society or excuse me, not my
Society, Micology Guild.
>> Thank you very much for that, Neville.
Um one second. Okay, next we have
Manuel. Um, I have allowed your mic.
Please unmute when ready and and begin.
Uh, good afternoon everyone. My name is
uh Manny Grigo and I am uh from
Albuquerque, born and raised here in
Albuquerque and I have no real
affiliations with any groups right now.
I'm just looking to get on this
committee and it's something I'm very
interested in and have been a part of
for a while. So looking to uh see where
this goes and help in any way I can. So
thank you guys for having me.
>> Thank you for that. Next we have Alan
Thomas.
Alan, I have allowed your mic. Please
unmute and begin when ready.
[snorts]
If you are experiencing any trouble, do
drop a line in the chat. Um and
typically what we have noticed that if
someone drops out of the chat and comes
back in uh that typically uh remediates
any any issues. Um so yeah uh let me let
let us know. So I will move on to the
next individual. We have John there. So
just going to allow Mike. John please
begin when ready.
>> Uh hi my name is John. Um I'm a home
micologist. Uh, I've done some work with
uh NM Fungi and Four Corners Fungi. Um,
I'm just here to help any way I can and
I'm here from New Mexico and this is uh
second committee meeting.
>> Thank you very much for that, John. Uh,
and just uh the comment by Alan there.
Uh, yeah, if you uh you may introduce
yourself on the chat. Um, and also again
if if you feel uh like it may benefit
maybe uh dropping off from the chat and
joining back in that that can uh and
often has uh solved the issue. Uh next
we have Brett. Brett I have allowed your
mic. Please unmute yourself and begin
when ready.
>> Hey, good afternoon everybody. Glad to
see you all again. My name is Brett
Phelps. Um I am an attorney based in Las
Vegas, New Mexico. I live in Mora, New
Mexico. um have no other affiliations
other than, you know, wanting to support
the program as as much as I can. I've
been going to a bunch of the committee
meetings. Um became especially
interested in this one after the last
full board meeting when it became clear
that this particular committee has got a
lot on their on their plate in a very
short period of time. Um so I've you
know this is yeah rules, regulations,
laws is what I what I do. So wanted to
just offer my help for that in any way I
can and uh happy to be here.
>> Thank you very much for that. Next we
have Gregory Evans. I have allowed your
mic. Please begin when ready.
>> Greetings once again everybody. Thank
you Chris for holding space. Um my name
is Gregory Evans. I'm here as an
independent researcher and micologist.
Um
I am
available to
produce any form of research writing
contributions that can promote the
successful function of this group which
I see as currently writing the
recommendation. um in E minuses. This is
like yesterday. [clears throat] I'm
currently working on a unified glossery
of terms that will be submitted for
community and committee review.
>> That's all.
>> Thank you very much for that. Um and
before I get to Scott, we just have two.
Alan Thomas. Hi, my name is Alan Thomas.
I have no business affiliations. I am
interested in the committee and what uh
is going on. Um next we have Tay Davis.
My name is Tay Davis. I'm a New Mexico
resident. I do not have any
affiliations. I just want to support by
serving on the committee.
So thank you for sharing. Uh next we
have Scott. Uh I have allowed your mic.
Um please uh unmute yourself and begin
when ready.
>> Hello. Uh my name is Scott Fulkman. I am
a chemistry professor at New Mexico
State University. I also am starting an
analysis lab primarily targeted at uh
state regulated cannabis uh for potency
and residual pesticides. Um I am also
interested in doing the potency analysis
of psilocybin mushrooms when things come
online. So our private lab that we are
creating, we also want to be able to do
uh and contribute in that way to the
potency and consistency testing of the
mushrooms that are cultivated in the
state.
>> Thanks.
>> Thank you very much for sharing. Um next
we have James.
James, I have enabled your mic. Please
unmute and begin when ready.
>> Great. Thank you. Hi everybody. James
Ferrer. Um, I am a software developer by
nature. I'm building the app. Actually,
we're releasing the app in two weeks
that uh will help uh manage the entire
backbone of this industry. So,
everything from cultivating spores to
long-term patient care and outcome
tracking. Um, yeah. So, happy to be here
and I want to make sure I get everything
you all come up with into this app so
that it perfectly matches what we're
trying to do here from a technology
standoint.
Incredible. Thank you very much for
sharing. And finally, uh, in the chat,
we have Eric Barlow. Uh, I am unable to
talk over voice. I'm Eric Barlow. I'm
from Idaho, but I've been cultivating
cannabis and mushrooms since I moved
away in 2019. And Greg Evans, uh, makes
another comment there at the bottom. I
forgot to clarify. I'm a new as a New
Mexico resident since 2019. No
affiliations.
So, with that, oh, we have, sorry, we
have another hand up there. Uh, and
that's Ben Edwards. Ben, I have enabled
your mic. Please begin when ready. Just
unmute and and Yeah.
>> Yeah. Hi, good afternoon everybody. I'm
Ben Edwards. I've lived in New Mexico
most of my life for about 50 years and
I'm an amateur micologist and have
worked in ceremonies for about 30 years.
Thanks.
>> Thank you, Ben, for that. And next in
the chat we have James Hassobe. Uh
greetings everyone. I'm James here. I'm
a biomedical research analyst affiliate
with the department of health in
Arizona. I'm rate I'm uh wanting to
learn more and it's great to be here. So
thank you for sharing that James. And
with that said that is all the comments
from all members. Um Chris I turn back
to you.
>> Uh thank you very much. Um, next, can
somebody put up the agenda and perhaps
um post it to the chat as well? Oh,
excellent. All [clears throat] right.
So, uh, just a few things we want to
talk about today. Um, next up is how to
do our documentation. If you want to
send something to the advisory board,
please, um, send it to the Department of
Health. If it's for specifically for
this committee, make sure you put that
in the subject line and that way we can
be transparent with our documents and um
and you know everything we are going to
try to accomplish in all the proposals
we're going to work through here in
committee. Um and so if you send those
proposals they can get become part of
the record of the last meeting and then
people can review them and we can you
know go through them and and kind of uh
take stuff and and bring it into these
discussions as we see fit. But uh I just
want to do this the correct way so we
are you know transparent about this
process and we are being fair for
everybody. So that's the appropriate way
to send documentation and make it part
of the the public record. Is that
correct, Dominic?
>> Yes, it is. And I do have that on the
slide that's on the screen right now
with that information. And I'll be
putting that in the chat here in just a
moment.
>> Excellent. Um, after this we're going to
hear from Tori Armbrist. I hope I said
your name right and learn about and a
little bit about lessons learned. I was
hoping to have a representative from
Colorado as well to see some of their
lessons learned in the cultivation
space. Um, but I might be able to get
somebody on it next week. Um,
[clears throat]
and then do has provided us an outline
that they uh are recommending we work
from and we'll go over that. Um I've
been kind of digging into the um
mushroom good goodalural
practices. Um so I wanted to talk about
that briefly. We we'll have a little bit
of time for proposals and then um talk
about what we're going to do at our next
meeting and uh have some time for
discussion hopefully. Um,
so with that said,
I'm going to turn it over to Tori if
you're ready to talk about lessons
learned in um
and what you've learned during your
working in this space.
Can we unmute Tori?
>> Yeah. So, actually Tori, I'm elevating
you to a presenter. So, uh, give me just
a moment to get that done. And you
should be a presenter now, Tori. And you
should be able to go ahead and speak.
And if you have any slides, you can
present those as well.
All right. Tori is not ready.
>> Dominic, you're on mute.
>> Oh, sorry. Yeah, Tori. Uh, I just want
to say your mic is live, but we're not
hearing anything.
>> We can come back to Tori. Maybe she's
not quite ready yet. or if you're having
trouble, please let us know in the chat.
Tori,
[clears throat]
is there anybody here from Colorado who
would like to share some lessons
learned?
If anyone wishes to speak, please uh
raise your hand so I can enable your
microphone. Um if you are yeah wondering
about that.
Tori's in the chat just uh specifying
that uh she's unmuted, but uh you all
can't seem to hear me. I'm sorry. Um it
may be uh ju just just try and give this
one a go. If you drop off the chat and
then maybe join back in, it may just um
fix that. It seems to have worked a few
times in the past for other participants
in the in the not too distant past. So
try that out and see what happens. And
we will uh continue on. And when you're
back, just uh raise your hand and and we
can we can pick up where we left off.
Sorry, Tori.
Okay. Um,
next up, uh, hopefully we can get Tori
back to report out from, uh, on her
lessons learned. Um,
let's pull up the DO provided outline,
please.
And while he uh while we're getting that
pulled up,
um couple things I wanted to talk about.
So I think at this stage in the game
we're looking for kind of just plain
language proposals of what we would like
to see in the program you know and then
throughout the process department of
health and you know the next level at
the advisory board we'll we'll kind of
start putting things into more legal
regulatory terms. Um, so we don't need
to to get too technical or anything here
and we want to
um try and
and keep this program as simple and as
broad as possible
um and not overregulate it. Right? So um
I've been trying to kind of feel that
balance out and and and figure out what
exactly is needed. I think all of us are
on a big learning curve right now. Um so
I I hope you all bear with the process
and um and we'll keep keep plugging away
as much as we can. Um
is that correct Dominic? Do I did I
mistake anything there?
>> No, you did. But if I can just add so
one of the things that we do want to
make sure uh and mind you this document
that we're sharing it's an outline. This
is not in by any ways finished draft.
It's a starting point. So there'll be
some things in here that we've actually
put in specifically because in the
previous meeting, not just the
propagation, but some of the others,
these are some of the points that have
brought up. And so they're here in many
ways just as a starting point, not as a
final point. Um so I just want to make
sure that's clear uh with regard to it.
And then the other aspect is we're
trying to also ensure as we move uh
potential recommendations for the
regulations forward that we are not
trying to overregulate everything that
for example a cultivator is doing. So
when we look at some of this we're
looking at things where we're there's
going to be some limitations. There will
be some other items. And Brett, you got
to one my final point before I turn it
back over to Chris, but I'll say it now
is that one of the things we're going to
do is we're going to get this posted. We
are and we have asked for it to be
expedited to be posted um for this so
that everyone can take a look at it
before, excuse me, before the next
meeting which is proposed right now for
the 30th. And so that way what would
happen is people would be able to review
it, see what's here, make their notes,
and then in the meeting we would be able
to discuss and bring them on up because
remember as Chris said earlier, we want
to keep this as a transparent process.
So we need to have those conversations
here in the public in the meeting rather
than in other areas as far as for the
recommendations themselves. I hope that
makes sense. Uh, I know it was a it's a
little bit much, but that's sort of what
we're looking at. And the thing to
remember with all of this is this is
within the bounds of the statute. There
are some things, and I've said this in
some of the other meetings where people,
for example, have requested and said
things like, well, why can't I just go
to a store, buy it, and use it at home?
And it's because it is a medical program
that needs to be done in approved
locations. And so, uh, regardless of
anything else, we have to stay within
the bounds of the statute. And so,
always keep that in mind. I will also
put here in just a moment the link to,
uh, the statute itself into the chat so
that people, if you haven't looked at it
and read through it before, especially
for this committee, I really recommend
reading through the entire bill and
through the entire statute to understand
what some of those limitations and what
some of those opportunities are. I hope
that helps. Anyway, with that, I'll turn
back on over to you, Chris, um as far as
uh moving forward and I will get the
link for the um regulation or for the
statute rather.
>> Excellent. Okay. So, this is kind of the
beginning document we're going to be
working from. And I I've also created a
a separate document for just um you know
plain language proposals as well that we
can kind of then add back into this and
and uh we'll Frankenstein it all
together eventually. But um
so um I guess we can just scan through
this. The the one I know that is going
to stick out to a lot of people right
off the bat is section two here. The
authorized species. I want to talk to
this real briefly. You know, I'm not
opposed like this is DOH's guidance,
right? And I'm not opposed to going
against the grain on this if the board
if this committee wants to recommend
something different. However, I will say
and you know, I I am actually for having
more species and cultivars available to
people. Um, I've had a lot of
conversations about all of this and I
think it would be a great way for
growers to differentiate themselves and
for facilitators to have some, you know,
a special connection with certain
medicine they use in their practice and
um, so I am for it. However, uh with the
safetymindedness of this medical
psilocybin,
uh program, I don't think we're going to
get a broad range approved through the
next level, which is the advisory board.
And if we were to, it still has to be
then put into um uh regulation by the
secretary of health. And I don't think
we would get that approved either. So
psilocybin cubensus is is going to be a
given. And if people can find [snorts]
the
studies or the documentation showing
that it, you know, others are safe, I I
think those would be great points to
bring up into this board and then we
could recommend more cultivars species
to be authorized. Um, but I just don't
think that's going to happen
immediately. Um,
and
we can I think we should continue maybe
just reviewing this um document and
maybe we can uh open it up for
discussion and proposals afterwards.
Okay. So, the the psilocybin program
goes off of a permit structure. It's
doesn't require a license. Um,
based on my conversations with Dominic,
uh, I know we're going to try to keep
all permitting, inspection, prices, and
all of that type of uh, you know,
aspects at low cost as possible. Um, so
again, these are just starting points
for recommendations.
Um, and we can continue
after we give everybody time to kind of
look at look through these and pick them
apart. And I would like to bring it back
into discussion next week and
um, edit this document and and and start
making approvals on it.
Does that make sense to everybody?
>> And Chris, if I can just clarify one
thing. I I just want to say a lot of
this comes it's not necessarily that
it's recommendations from the
department. It's based in uh as far as
from the different statutes and
regulations from Colorado, Oregon, some
of the proposals from some of the other
states such as Maryland, Massachusetts,
and some other areas sort of kind of
cobbled together quite frankly. And then
what we've also done is based upon
comments that have been made in other
meetings, not just propagation, but for
example, there's been quite a few
comments made in like the equity
meeting, in the research meeting, and in
other areas so that we um have that. And
Greg, like I said, what we're doing is
we're going to post this online. Um
trying to post it all into the chat
right now. This is just so that people
have an idea. This is what's coming up.
Um so that we have that there. Um, and
we're still have a little bit that we're
actually working as far as putting it
into it so that we can get it posted
here in the next couple of days. So,
we're going to have that. Again, this is
more just so people have an idea and are
able to think about some of the
questions um and so that we have that
moving forward. But I can increase the
size a little bit. So, I'll increase the
size a little. Hopefully that helps with
being able to view it.
Are there any questions so far on
anything before we continue moving on?
Okay. All right. Um,
>> Johnny,
>> we have one. Yeah. One second. Johnny,
go ahead. Um uh I think possibly just
for clarity for everybody, it might just
be good to literally just read through
um just so everybody has a chance to um
just see the contents cuz um I think
just scanning it a couple uh you know
like um just views on that might I I
don't know if everybody's going to get
the information they need.
Okay, I can read it if uh you'll go back
up to the top, Dominic.
And
>> and Chris, if you like, I can go I can
read it through. I'm happy to do so.
[laughter]
>> I think you've got a a a better reading
voice than I do, Dominic. So, go ahead.
>> Sure.
>> Okay. All right. So, uh we'll just start
purpose and scope. is establish a
regulated framework for the lawful
propagation, production, testing, and
preparation of psilocybin products in
New Mexico. Emphasize public health,
safety, consistency, and traceability.
Minimize duplication by utilizing
existing state, county, and municipal
licensing and inspection authorities.
And then I see there's a hand raised.
>> Yes. Uh, Desg Garcia, I have enabled
your mic. Please go ahead.
Um,
pardon me. You may now speak if you'd
like.
Okay,
it seems they've lowered their hands.
Dominic, you may go ahead. Uh if there's
uh there's a few uh m please raise your
hand again if you wish to speak. Uh and
I will yeah make sure to uh address
that.
>> No worries. And uh Ishmael uh just
because with going through the reading
it's hard for me to look at both
screens. So if someone else raises their
hand if you can just keep an eye and
please interrupt me. Don't worry about
that part. I will not take it as being
rude. So all right. Uh so the second
part uh authorized species um
psilocybensis
shall be the authorized species for
cultivation and production. Other
species or cultivars may be considered
for approval upon submission to the
department with evidence. Recommend at
least three peer-reviewed studies
demonstrating safety and potency. The
exception to this is for research
proposals which will be determined once
the medical psilocybin research fund
process and protocols are promulgated
and based on funding capacity
and I'm pausing just in case
uh anybody
>> we have one comment in the chat um
attendees can you increase the size of
your screen by uh just uh basically
zooming in a little bit more Dominic um
>> I was just giving instructions how
attendees can improve the size of your
stream.
>> Pardon me. Sorry, I thought that was I
was thinking that that's right.
[laughter]
>> Yeah, there's actually a couple
different ways that you can do that. If
you notice in the bottom lefthand
corner, there's Dominic's name and a
minus and plus that can resize. You can
also click on the pop out button on your
menu bar and that'll actually take the
presentation out of this mode and and
enlarge it. Couple different ways to do
that.
Thank you, Kathy. And as you all can
tell, uh we uh here in the program try
to enjoy what we're doing, which is why
you'll hear laughter on a regular basis
from us. Uh we take it very seriously,
but still we should all enjoy life as
much as we can. In any case, so number
three, permit structure. um primary
psilocybin production permit issued by
the department required for cultivation,
harvest, processing, packaging, applying
persons. And just as a note here,
persons just is the legal term that's
used for organizations, companies, all
of that. So I know it sounds a little
odd when you're saying just persons in
this context, but you may hear that in
various areas, but that means the
organization or the company that's doing
this. Applying persons can apply for one
or any aspect of the permit. Demonstrate
psilocybin containing mushrooms products
are kept in a secure location. Double
locks, video surveillance, alarm system,
keypad entry.
Uh and then business facility and
occupancy compliance, proof of ownership
of the land, facility or written
approval from the owner, i.e. lease
specifying use to include psilocybin
cultivation and production.
business license in the state of New
Mexico, proof of registration with New
Mexico State Secretary of State, local
building and safety authorities
including certificate of occupancy, fire
code compliance, electric and HVAC
inspections, and no new specs psilocybin
specific building standards unless
explicitly necessary.
And the reason we say that is some well
you'll see here in a little bit as far
as local uh local areas and governments
may require additional items. Um zoning
and municipal municipal permits must be
within the geographical boundaries of
New Mexico. City and county planning or
zoning departments land use loose via
pardon me everyone. It has been a long
little bit of a long day, but uh land
use approval, conditional use permits
where applicable, for example, city of
Albuquerque raw food permit, food safety
training certification for employees,
and note that local governments retain
zoning authority consistent with
existing agriculture or light industrial
classifications.
From the agricultural standpoint, uh
note we are still seeking some more
information regarding this. uh New
Mexico Department of Agriculture, NMDA.
And we do, by the way, hope that some of
those who are engaging in cultivation
currently uh for uh other mushrooms and
other potential uh vegetables and um
plants might be able to assist with
regard to the licensing side uh as far
as determining exactly what's needed.
But to ensure that uh that all cultivar
cultivators utilize pest and
contamination mitigation guidance from
NMDA
production is treated analogously to
controlled environment agriculture
uh cultivation standards. Well, and
before I go on any questions or comments
so far?
Okay. uh cultivation standards. Growth
medium. Growth medium is not restricted.
All substrates and inputs must be
documented, tracked by batch and fully
disclosed on final product labeling.
Environmental controls indoor or
controlled environment cultivation
required controls documented for
temperature, humidity, air exchange,
biocurity measures to prevent
crosscontamination.
No pesticides or fungicides utilized.
Okay. And there is a question here. Uh
just about to Yep. Shane uh McDaniel,
please go ahead. Um I've enabled your
mic. Uh unmute yourself and
>> Yes. I just want to validate something
by air exchange. Are you talking about
they'll need to monitor CO2 levels
or just
some minute per hour
air exchange or by cubic foot? How how
are we
do you know how they're um going to
expect environmental controls on air
exchange?
>> Uh Shane, that is actually a part of
what needs to be determined. So it's a
great question.
Okay.
>> Yeah.
>> Thank you. Have a comment there in the
chat as well, Dominic.
>> Before we do that, Shane, do you have a
recommendation on which direction?
>> I know that you've done some cultivation
yourself. So,
>> so yeah. So, generally when they're
talking about air exchange, they're
talking about making sure that the CO2
levels are um low enough um and they
don't get too high. So, I would say the
air exchange needs to be done through
CO2 monitoring. And when the CO2 levels
get too high, it turns on a it turns on
a fan that uh or an exhaust or something
that gets the air exchanged, right?
>> Sure.
>> Okay, great. So, I put in for CO2 levels
and monitoring. Okay. Thank you. We
don't have to the the good part about
regulations is we don't have to get into
details as to you know what exactly
those mechanisms as far as like fans
that sort of thing but that's good to
know it's actually very helpful. So
thank you. Uh and then Ishmael I think
you said there was something in the
chat.
>> Yes there's a comment in the chat fungal
gnat
uh remediation may be something to
address. Uh this is from Gregory Evans
and and he goes on to say FAE is a
common cultivation concept for
mushrooms.
>> So what I'm hearing is that there may
need to be fungicides utilized but uh
still no on pesticides. Is that correct?
>> I will uh see what they say. Uh Estavan
says, "I would think FAE would be
adequate as specific CO2 levels do not
pose consumer risk when isolated as a
single factor." Alan Thomas then says,
"I disagree with CO2 monitoring. It is
expensive and unnecessary for the most
part."
Remember everyone, if you uh wish to
comment, you can also uh speak. Uh just
remember raise your hand and uh you can
enable your mic.
Can I get somebody willing to
talk to me? What What is F What are we
talking with FAE? I'm I'm assuming the
last two are air exchange,
but [clears throat]
>> So, we have uh Gregory there with their
hand raised. I will uh Gregory, your mic
is enabled if if you care to uh speak or
answer the question that uh was posed by
Chris as well.
>> Yeah, Chris. Uh FAE is a just a common
term for or like an acronym for fresh
air exchange. Uh the concept of fresh
air exchange in micological growth is it
is one of the triggers that causes
primordia to develop on the surface of a
substrate. Adjusting the CO2 levels
during the process of a grow is
something that is highly variable
depending on context and purpose. Um
there are genetic isolations that do
well in high CO2
environments such as grow bags and there
are
other variants like more wild variants
that are going to do better with way
more air.
As far as monitoring it, I think that
should be a facility's decision. I think
that there is a huge value from a
research perspective and in like say we
have like like a growing
uh software that monitors your growth
cycle and your harvest. It could be an
option in that, but I don't think it
should be something that is defined in
this recommendation to say you need this
level of CO2. I just think that that
would be over regulating.
>> Okay.
>> Thank you, Greg. So, what I'm hearing
>> anymore.
>> Yeah. No, no, no. That was that was
really helpful, Greg. Um, and so what
I'm actually hearing with regard to all
of this and I'm just trying to do it so
I document it. Uh, is that it's as far
as ensuring that there's uh fresh just
to ensure there's a fresh air exchange
with regard to that. Is that what I'm
getting on it? Uh, and if I could get um
from people if you could do a thumbs up
in the um you know use the emoticons the
react button. Uh does that work or is
that what people are talking about? We
have a few comments in the chat here I
think are talking about it. Uh Alan
Thomas specifies the PQenses do not need
frequent air exchange twice daily for a
limited time is sufficient. Estavan
Hernandez says, "Honestly, FA may not
even be a relevant parameter uh as many
growers use in vitro grow methods such
as bags and tubs." James Ferrer says,
"As we are just talking, are we just
talking facility as a simple home CO2
detector should be sufficient? Growing
CO2 is not growing CO2 is not related to
uh personal safety."
>> Uh and we also have John there. Sorry.
Mushrooms actually need some CO2 to
induce pinning.
That's all the comments there in the
chat.
>> So, this seems like a business decision
and maybe something that we should
completely take out of this document and
not need to uh have regulations on.
That's the the kind of take I'm getting
from everybody here.
>> If I if I'm still permitted, um I would
suggest that in from a regulation
standpoint, we would strike something
like strike all of this. I think
environmental controls around safety,
fire protection, health, um employees
like spore count in the air for
employees, stuff like that could be
valuable from the field facility
regulation perspective. Um as far as
like techniques for growing, I think
that those are IP and you know more more
specific to the individual grower as
long as they don't cross like a a safety
threshold,
>> right? And thank you. That's actually
really important and that's a part of as
what we're talking about or what I was
mentioning in the beginning is we do not
want to be overregulating. So if this is
a difference in just how somebody is
growing and is not actually something
that needs to be regulated, we do want
to remove it. So I did see as you were
saying that and I think that was Greg
that you were speaking, but I did see
multiple thumbs up during that point
when you were saying that as far as
removing. Can I get thumbs up again if
that is indeed the the idea that this is
not something that's needed from a
regulatory standpoint, but really just
is an individual cultivator's uh
preference in their growing practices.
>> I can see the grower showed up here.
>> I'm seeing that. Yes. No, and that's
perfect. That's exactly what we want to
hear. Uh I, by the way, if anybody
hasn't figured out, I'm actually more
for less regulation than for more
regulation. So, okay, that sounds great.
Um, if that's okay, we'll go ahead and
move on. And I've struck that, by the
way, out of this.
>> And I'll mute.
>> Yep. [laughter]
Thank you. All right. Uh, so where were
we? Oh, the, uh, next question was about
fungicide. That was something in the
chat. Uh, sorry, let me go back and see.
Uh, was that something that we need to
just leave in for the moment? Um, or,
uh, that we need needs to be looked at.
Is that again something that uh the idea
being is that if fungicides are used,
we're going to have to test for them
just to let everybody know. If it is
that they are not allowed, then we while
we would still have to test in the end
product, it would not be tested at other
points. What are people thinking
regarding that?
And I bring it up because there was the
comment in the chat, but I can't I can't
find it myself at the moment. Uh I
believe the point was by um Eric Barlow
who stated if sterilized uh through the
process you shouldn't need any
fungicides or pesticides from my
experience and this is here I'm speaking
as Eric um fungicides kill fungus lol
not needed that was Eric Parker
>> okay so what I'm kind of hearing right
now is to leave the no fungicides
utilized correct
>> um yeah so far we have a hand up by uh
Gregory Evans Uh Gregory, do you have
any points?
>> About everything. Um again, this goes
down to cultivator preference. Um when
we are cultivating mushrooms, we are
creating an environment that is ideal
for multiple organisms to grow in a
controlled environment. Whereas out in
nature, they you know they like
tricoderma, for example, doesn't out
compete mushrooms. They all find their
own space. Um there are certain fungus
and bacteras that will grow in your
substrate and out compete your mcelium
if not sterilized proper properly. We
don't want to force if we are not going
to control substrate. We do not want to
force people to sterilize their
substrate. There are certain substrates
that do better in pasteurization,
keeping wild
um you know competing bacterias in the
process of growing like beneficial
bacteria, things that cause the the
micelium to strengthen in a certain way
or whatever. If say you're growing in an
open air warehouse where you just have
racks with heating over them but open
air flowing, you may want to utilize a
fungicide in your substrate to prevent
certain types of funguses from outco
competing your intended mycelial growth.
Um I can provide a paper on that.
>> Sure. So the question then is and here's
where the this is part of where the
balance comes in is if we allow for
fungicides to be used that means they
have to be tested for.
>> I don't think that that's that I I mean
that it is a cost on the far end of it
but we do need to be yeah I don't know
maybe we just pin it and talk about what
we're te like what testing looks like
and what the costs are and what the
requirements are. when something goes to
market, we need to match. We need to do
our best efforts to hit FDA standards
whether they're involved or not. Like we
need to be like 10 times ahead of
um those standards. I'll yield to Scott.
I see he's got something to say.
>> Yes. And before we get to Scott, we just
have two comments in the chat. Both Ali
stating, "Aren't there already standards
for pesticide use for commercial
consumable sorry for consumable
mushrooms?" That was their comment. And
then you have Alan. Uh testing for
contamination will be necessary
including molds in the final product.
Estavan uh triric triricodama
and uh hyperyces uh mitigation can be
done organically. Um hydrogen peroxide
can be used within USDA organic
compliance.
Those are the comments there. Scott
Fulman I have your mic is enabled.
Please begin when ready.
>> Thank you. Um so I speak I wanted to
reflect on the um testing of fungicides
because in the cannabis space there are
several different pesticides that are
required to be tested for regardless of
their use or not because secondary
contamination can occur even if it's
unintentional.
Um so my opinion is that testing for the
fungicides will be probably necessary
anyways and in most analytical labs that
would be doing the testing for the
psilocybin potency they would be able to
do the fundicide testing there as well.
Um and I would also like to comment that
the other possible biological
contaminants will need to be tested for
and the same thing with cannabis. There
are um aspiggillis, ecoli, and
salmonella are all tested for already on
flower that's grown in the field. And if
these are going to need to be tested for
anyway, um I think the decision of
whether or not to use fungicide is
probably up to the grower, but it
probably needs to be required regardless
of whether it's allowed be to be used or
not.
>> Thank you, Scott.
Those
are all comments so far.
>> Okay. All right. So,
is it again uh uh basically what people
are saying is to just simply remove
fungicides from this location?
Can I get thumbs up if it is to remove
it from here?
I'm not seeing it. Oh, there's one, two,
couple others. Okay, so we'll take that
on out.
All right, fantastic. Thank you. So,
this is exactly the kinds of things that
we were talking about that we wanted to
be able to do. All right, so batch uh
harvesting, processing, and
homogenization batch definition. A batch
defined as a single harvest lot
processed under uniform conditions, no
regulated size requirement.
batches must be fully homogenized prior
to testing.
Uh homogenization requirements that
physical homogenization is required to
ensure consistent potency across the
batch and the purpose behind this just
is accurate potency testing, reduction
of dose variability. Okay, and that's
just what we have there.
>> Uh Gregory Evans, uh your mic is
enabled. Please
go ahead
>> me again. Um I see there's a bunch of
comments. Um I just think that we're
running the risk with this language of
preventing whole fruit distribution and
um I just want to call that out. Um I
think that batch sampling from say you
have a 10 pound harvest um you send like
x amount of that whatever percentage is
defined by law to the facility that is
testing they pull random sampling that
are you know defined in their protocols
their SOPs and then um they homogenize
that for test
just
>> thank you very much for that And we have
a uh
>> comment there from Shane McDaniel. For
the same reason, should we even regulate
temperature and humidity requirements?
[snorts]
>> Um and Dominic there uh those were also
removed, Shane. Um next we have Scott
Faultman. Uh your mic is enabled, Scott,
please. I Hello again. Um so I I totally
agree with the idea of the physical
homogenization. I'd just like to point
out that sometimes during the
homogenization process, it can cause the
decomposition of psilocybin and there's
going to need to be a careful um
approach to how the homogenization is
done if it's done to a full batch
because it also makes it prone to
oxidation and so you'd have to be very
careful about whole body mushrooms that
have been homogenized into a powder for
example and how they're stored
subsequently.
>> Thank you for that.
Next we have Brett Phelps.
Your mic is enabled. Please begin when
ready.
>> All right. Yeah, thanks guys. Um, so I
Yeah, I have an issue here with this
definition of batch and how it's it's
used um compared to, you know, how how
the batches and testing is done in the
medical cannabis and the the idea that a
batch is a single harvest lot. um rather
than rather than splitting up batches
into lots for for more specific testing.
I think this is the exact issue that
happened in in Oregon that led to uh
really exploding testing costs. when
you're talking about every single
harvest event being a a new batch that
requires testing, the way that that um
mushrooms are harvested, you know,
through different flushes. Um
essentially, you have, you know, if you
do a flush on on Monday and then you do
a flush again on your second flush on on
Wednesday that are in the exact same,
you know, it's in the exact same
substrate, exact same growing
conditions, everything else. um to have
those then have to both be tested
separately when when they're essentially
all the all the same and could be broken
up in a different way um I think is
going to lead to some exploding costs in
the uh in the the way that things are
done. If we look at the at the cannabis
regulations, you know, they your your
batches um are are an identified
quantity that's harvested during the
same specified time period with all the
same cultivation. Um and then within
those batches, you can test lots and and
that also helps if you have recall
issues or things like that. you're not
having to destroy an entire um you know
an entire bit if it's only a small bit
that's actually um that's actually a
problem. And so I think I I think really
looking at that and and how this this
definition as it was used in in Oregon I
think was a huge part of the problem
that led to the you know the exploding
of costs there that has you know led to
a lot of these places going out of
business already. um as well as yeah how
we you know how we do it in in the
medical cannabis side. Um you know I
don't so um I I think that that's
definitely something that that should be
looked at. Um I think that you know it
it allows for allowing for lot testing.
Um
will will be able to make things much
more pinpointed. Um, additionally,
yeah, if you if you do it over a time
aggregate, you know, you're not going to
have this exploding number of batches
that all have to be tested. Um, the side
the the no size limits, I think, can
lead to um arbitrary outcomes as far as
as far as what's considered a batch
here. Um, and and those type of things.
So, I I think that's just an area that
should definitely um take a take a
closer look at and think about. Do we
want to do this exactly how Oregon did
or do we want to do it, you know, closer
to how we do it in in medical cannabis
in a way that um is is more functional
for the producers.
>> Thank you for that. We have some
comments in the chat just to uh bring
up. Um Alan Thomas says, "Physical
homogenation uh is somewhat vague.
Fruits will be a variety of sizes. Uh,
fruits will be a variety of sizes will
always be harvested if you maintain a
constant harvesting schedule. This is
followed up by a comment by James
Ferrer. Mushrooms don't seem to care
about our schedule when it comes to
fruiting. Followed up by uh a hands up
by Estavan. Uh, please I have enabled
your mic. Go ahead.
>> Uh, yes. When it comes to uh testing
standards, a batch definition,
monogenization, all of that I think is
neatly tied up and analyzed through
relative standard deviation. Uh for
example, in Oregon, they have a pass
fail line at 20% relative standard
deviation on a lot. Meaning if there's
more than a 20% difference in uh testing
parameter, excuse me, potency testing uh
from lowend to highend and the batch
would fail. I think that's a good uh
sort of benchmark for homogenization of
whole fruing body. Um, additionally,
they do have a lot definition of a batch
being smaller than 1 kilogram, which I
would think would be pretty reasonable.
>> Thank you for that. We have another
comment in the chat there, John, um, who
says, "The powderization will also cause
the product to become even more uh,
hydrophilic than the whole fruits." Uh,
finally, we have Gregory Evans. Gregory,
your mic is enabled. Please go ahead.
Gregory
>> unmuting the mic helps.
>> Um I wanted to say I think this whole
section deserves a work group. Um, I
think that
coming together and like
just hammering language on this concepts
like could be something to come back
with like a more defined refined uh
suggestion. I know that there's you know
like I could do that by myself and
everyone could do them by themselves. I
would love to see some of the mines get
together, but again need to do that
within the compliance of the um whatever
statute that is. Um
as far as batches, it could be argued
that like a single inoculation point. So
say you so in Colorado they have like
you can do this mount this number of
this size tubs, right? We don't want to
like tell people they have to grow in
tubs or tell people they have to grow
away, but like say we have like say I'm
a cultivator. I'm going to I have 500
bags and I have enough liquid culture
that I have prepared to inoculate those
bags. That inoculation can produce four,
five, six flushes depending on the
cultivar out of that in out of that
unique
cake inside that bag.
If we could define
that as a batch, that would leave a lot
of room for um kind of like
final output testing just to kind of
brainstorming.
I think the intention on this is to
leave it as broad as we can and that way
batch size isn't necessarily pinned down
and if you harvest 10 pounds of
mushrooms then you would have the same
testing requirements is if you harvested
you know one pound of of mushrooms under
those uniform conditions which I would
imagine is you know that that um
>> inoculation or however However, you're
you're growing those mushrooms and and
uh you know, but the larger
sample size you take, right, it would
really come down to that standard
deviation that
Estavan [clears throat]
was Yeah. was mentioning.
>> Yeah. And that that puts it into a
conversation about scale and like do we
have small growers and boutique growers
and largecale facilities? Is this
full-on agriculture? or is this like a
craft that somebody designs for Etsy? I
will yield.
>> We have uh James Ferrer with their hand
up. Uh James, um you may speak.
>> Yeah, I think there's a lot of tricky
nuances here. You know, you know, when
you think about the process, it's not
just, you know, a single flush. You'll
have a bag that might flush five times.
And the consistency of the psilocybin in
each of those flushes could be quite a
bit different. you know, and and
typically it's a week cycle. But if
you're, you know, if you're a large
producer and maybe you've got, you know,
50 or 100 bags going, you know, then,
you know, that would make a lot of sense
to be testing weekly as you harvest,
dry, and and then, you know, powder
them. Uh, but for a smaller producer, if
you're testing four times a month at,
you know, $200 a pop, it's going to get
really expensive unless you're a fairly
large operation. So, you know, I guess
the concept would be you'd want to be
able to go through several flushes,
[snorts] dry them, and then powder them
all at once, and then do your testing so
that you're not, you know, so you might
have monthly cycles as opposed to weekly
cycles or daily cycles just depending on
the size of the operation. And it does
leave out how do you handle fresh if we
if we even say fresh is okay, how do we
handle that? because that's going to
vary quite a bit and there's probably
not enough time to send off fresh
mushrooms to get tested, get the results
back and then ship them to a provider
um before they go bad, right? They only
last about two weeks in the fridge.
>> Thank you for that. We have a hand up
there by Brett Phelps. Uh please uh your
mic is enabled. Please begin when ready.
>> Yeah, thanks. Just wanted to really echo
what James had just brought up of the,
you know, taking into consideration the
the the current Yeah. As as James was
describing, under the current definition
there, each one of those would all have
to be Yeah. would all have to be tested,
which I think for a large industrial
producer is going to be great, but if or
not a problem, but if we're really
looking to, you know, have this be
something that's available to small New
Mexico businesses that um yeah, that
that doing it under this current
definition is is going to be cost
prohibitive.
>> Thank you everyone. And just um as a
reminder, the uh the situation here and
what we're kind of doing is to go over
these to also find the points that we
really need to be focusing in a little
bit more and the different areas and I
will tell you the language on this has
actually changed several times as we are
doing it and as you all have here heard
in this different people have different
ideas on how to do that. So what I would
recommend is we put a pin on this
conversation for the moment and when we
come back next week or uh in the week
and a half that we devote some time to
actually crafting what the language
should be. So that gives people time to
think about it and how do we exactly
define this because remember the part
that we're looking at and this is why
some of the language as I say is a
little more broad at the moment with
some specificity to bring out the
discussion is because uh we're going to
be looking at this from an angle of how
do we actually encourage uh there to be
as you know different cultivators. How
do we encourage that without creating a
situation where it does price everybody
out if they're at a smaller size versus
a larger size and so that there can be
variation in those companies,
organizations or people who are growing
and uh we want to try to be able to do
that and it's a very difficult prospect
quite frankly and so we want your help
with it and that's why we wanted to
present today have some discussion but
really that really getting into the
details in the next meeting and um and
as much as I also like you know some
people have said can we get a few people
together separately again then we hit
into the whole idea that this is
supposed to be those few people together
separately and we don't want to create
subgroups of subgroups of subgroups we
want to keep it here so that it's
transparent it's public and if it means
we take a little bit of time you know if
it takes 30 minutes to go through and
figure out that language then that's
what we do um and that's That's that
part of it. And so really so far what
we're seeing is this is the biggest area
so far that we're coming across. But as
we get this posted up, please do read
through it. Um again, we'll have it
within the next couple of business days
um to be able to be up um and then be
able to go through it. But with that,
um, if it's okay with everybody, I'm
going to go ahead and continue moving
forward with us knowing that this idea
of the homogenization and the batch is
an area that we need to focus on in the
next meeting. Is that okay and
acceptable?
>> Sounds good. Dominic, one one thing I I
I heard somebody might be in the waiting
room. So, if there if we got people
waiting, can we please admit them?
>> There's nobody in the waiting room.
Yeah, we're pretty quick on that part,
but yeah, sometimes we do miss. So,
thank you for letting us know just in
case.
Okay. Uh testing and quality quality
assurance. And this, by the way, is the
other part where we're going to need
additional information. I will tell you,
we have gotten inundated with various
um proposals, ideas behind how testing
should occur. So I just want to make
sure that everybody realizes that when
we get to this, this is a part that we
need a lot of assistance, different
ideas and really working through this
committee to determine what happens. So
just to make sure everybody's aware of
that part as we go into it. Um so
testing authority testing is performed
by department approved laboratories. Uh
requirements for laboratories to be
approved. Uh and this first part is
something that we've mentioned several
times is that existing te cannabis
testing laboratories um and so what
we've talked about in some of the other
meetings is that for example if uh
somebody has already gone through the
testing process and gotten approved to
be a cannabis testing laboratory in New
Mexico then they we would they just
would have to do a simple application to
apply show they're in good standing and
then they would be also approved to test
for psilocybin
um ISO EC7025
accredited labs and then labs approved
or overseen by the department. Just so
people understand, when we're talking
labs approved or overseen by the
department, we're really talking about
the state lab uh department. So SLD for
those who are familiar with it. Okay.
And I see Scott Folkman has a hand up.
Uh
hi. Um so I think it's a great idea to
um use the cannabis testing
laboratories. Um but I would point out
that the extraction and testing of
psilocybin is quite a bit different than
potency testing for cannabis because of
the nature of the chemistry involved.
Psilocybin is a rather fragile molecule
um that has to be extracted properly in
order for consistent accurate analysis
as opposed to THC or THCA that's
relatively robust and quite easy to test
for. So I think that um any cannabis
labs that want to transition to do both
should still have um SOPs and they
should still have uh an accreditation
where they are able to accurately
identify the amount of psilocybin in a
known batch.
>> Thank you for that. We have one coming
from Gregory. Um, are we going to be
recommended standards uh for testing
SOPs? Um, and next one from James. Going
back to permits, it seemed like there
were several types. Need to scroll up.
Which ones would be required to test?
>> Okay. Uh, I'll tackle James' first
because that's really easy. This would
be a separate type of permit. Those
others were with regard to harvesting or
cultivation and harvest uh harvest
aspect. This is actually testing which
would be a different permit. Um, so, uh,
we have that and Greg, uh, as far as the
standards for testing SOPs, that's
actually a part of it. That's a part of
what needs to be developed.
So, uh, okay. And, uh, so moving
forward. Oh, Scott.
>> Yep. We have Yeah.
>> Hey, sorry. Um, so for the cannabis, uh,
testing, there is not a required um, SOP
um, format. However, SOPs are required.
So each currently each testing lab is
required to develop their own SOPs that
are functional. Um and I think that
makes sense here as well because there
are different ways to test uh different
instruments. Some are more or less
expensive. But I think in the end as
long as there's accuracy then I think
that it'll work. And I I think having a
standard set of SOPs that are required
to be followed um would be
overregulating.
>> Thank you Scott.
And next we have Gregory. Please go
ahead.
>> I'm just reading through this and stop
me if we've already gotten to this. Um,
but I think at some point we should
define alkaloids to report on a minimum
like panel. Um, and then also like you
know market can allow for extended
testing and stuff like that. like we're
not going to require testing for,
you know, research type things. Um
whereas like we should definitely hit
the top five like the main active
alkyoids. Um
>> but I don't know like how do we
>> how do we define that?
>> Yeah, thank you Greg. that is actually
further down where it has some of those
and again some of those like for example
Estavon has in the chat right now about
some of the particular requirement from
Colorado and that's actually part of
what we're going to be asking and we're
going to be asking for a little bit more
in the next uh the next meeting again
this is just sort of the generalized
framework at the moment those specifics
we do need to be added though
>> definitely would we would we want to
bring in Um
I mean I have a few people that I would
bring into that conversation um if it's
on a schedule um
as far as like
really detailedmemes
in that space. Um also that poor CODMT
thing man like people in Colorado are
just throwing or throwing things in
their batches wildly
like people are pumping their stock.
>> Yeah. And again, Greg, people are
welcome to come to this meeting to be
able to participate and contribute and
uh you know, this is something we're
going to be looking at next in the next
meeting.
>> So,
>> cool. Definitely. I will I'll let a few
people know. Thank you.
>> Okay. And so, uh I'm going to go ahead
and continue to move forward. Um so,
again, required testing panels. And
again, this is the part that there's
going to be we need to get and we would
like from this group without us really
saying here's what you do, but we did
put an example in with regard to heavy
metals just so everybody's aware. Um,
but it is just an example and so we
would like the same as far as microbial
and some of the other um uh some of the
other potential contaminants. So testing
occurs once the batch is homogenized and
end products. Uh if the product is older
than 6 months, it needs to be retested.
The department can require additional
tests if there are complaints, concerns,
or at random. No cultivation or
processing facility will be asked to
test more than four times a year with
regard to random testing except if there
are contaminants or false statements
made by the organization, facility, or
on the labels. Um, just as a note about
that, what we're trying to do, the four
times a year is really just a starting
point as far as a talking point. What we
wanted to do is we want to ensure that
um, while I don't think that I would be
turning around and asking cultivators to
test, test, test test, test test all the
time. It is possible that someone down
the road could do that. We wanted to
make sure there were also protections
for the cultivators so that if there's
somebody who for example just doesn't
like them that they're not suddenly
getting required to test all the time
because of a personal issue. And so we
wanted to make sure that there are
protections there as well. Um and so
that's why we have that as far as the
random testing except if there are
complaints or uh other contaminants
found. So, uh, just as an example, um,
potency, psilocybin, and psilocin
concentration equivalency. Um, and I'm
not going to try to read all of this
because quite frankly, my Latin is
pretty good, but it's not that good. Um,
but it does have the five basis, which I
think Greg was getting at earlier.
Contaminant testing, and it we have here
microbial, heavy metals, and as I said,
this is the example for the heavy metal
testing. um pesticides, fungicides, and
then residual solvents. And if there are
other areas where we need to add in, of
course, that is uh something that we uh
would want to potentially do down the
road or I mean uh we would want to add
in at the next meeting. Thank you. Uh
Scott, I see your hand has raised.
>> Yes. Um so I just wanted to make a
comment on the heavy metals. Um those
actually do add a significant cost in
terms of testing. So, in the cannabis
space, typically the soil and the water
are tested. If municipal water is used,
it's not tested. It's not required to be
tested, but the soil is required to be
tested. I don't think a lot of
cultivators are actually doing that. Um,
but I just wanted to point that out that
if heavy metals testing is required, it
will add a significant cost to the
analysis because it requires a
completely different set of instruments
that are rather expensive.
>> Thank you for that. Thank you. We have a
message in the chat as well. That six
month uh retest is that for wholesale
stock at the bulk level and not for the
packaged products. Right.
>> Well, that's a part of what has to be
determined, Greg. Um in part it's going
to depend on whether it's already
packaged.
>> Fantastic. And there's another little
comment there from Alan Thomas. Yearly
usage in Oregon is about 15 kilos per
year for the whole set for the whole
state based on information from the
state in the first four months of 2025.
This is definitely going to be a niche
industry. Overregulation will make it
economically unfeasible quickly.
Expensive testing will do the same.
>> And as I said, yeah, thank you Alan.
That's one of the reasons and also thank
you to Scott with regard to the comment
about the cost on the heavy metals is
that's a part of why we don't want to
over uh create a situation where it is
going to be uh economically unfeasible.
We do recognize that and so that's a
part of why we're bringing this all here
and again as I said this this example
with the heavy metals is an example. So
we definitely want to hear as far as in
the next meeting especially as far as
what people think is going to be viable,
what is going to be workable and how we
actually set those limits to ensure that
testing does not price people out of the
industry.
So, I want to really make that part
clear because there are the there are
people who have said you must test for
all of these things. And I'll be quite
frank, it's in some cases I'm like, if
we're testing for that, there's actually
going to be no product left even after
the grows uh for people to even utilize.
So, how can we do that much testing? And
others who have said absolutely no
testing. So, we have to figure out
what's going to be safest for people and
yet still allow for this to work
economically.
Um, does that help?
Okay. All right. We're I'll continue to
move forward. So, batch release only
batches of course that pass all required
testing may be released for use.
All right. And then food preparation and
product handling. Um this really is any
conversion of raw material into
ingestible or prepared products is
subject to food safety oversight for
example through environmental health
food safety divisions. What we would be
requesting and requiring is that people
go through the appropriate food safety
and handling training certification.
That is different in different
municipalities and counties through the
state. For example, Albuquerque and
Berningo County have their own whereas
in other areas of the state there are
different ones that are there. and uh of
course no exemptions from standard food
safety requirements.
And that's where we are at the moment.
Uh any questions, comments about that
last bit before we jump forward to the
next? No.
No. All right. Well, thank you all. I
appreciate Oh, we've got one. Uh sorry,
I missed that.
>> We have James there with their hands up.
>> Okay.
>> Please go ahead.
Yeah. I So I was thinking more about,
you know, compart compartmentalizing,
you know, businesses. So you may just
grow and grow fruing bodies, fresh ones,
and then send them to a business that is
a more of a manufacturer that dries them
and, you know, turns them into some kind
of a product, chocolates or whatever. Um
would they I mean obviously it seems
like you would only require the testing
for the final stage but you know do do
we have it in a in a way that you could
do that where you have different
businesses doing different things but
not everybody has to test because at
some point that's just that's going to
kill things like Oregon is doing where
it's just so expensive for a patient to
to receive care.
>> Thank you James. That's actually a great
uh comment and it is actually why I I've
scrolled back up to that part where the
permits would be for and again these
were the ones that as we've looked at
other things cultivation, harvest,
processing, um packaging and then that
applying persons can apply for one or
any aspect of the permit.
So that would allow exactly what you're
talking about.
So now Dominic, we have just one comment
in the chat which I thought I'd
highlight. uh by John Esleik. Um I have
to leave the meeting. I just wanted to
suggest that we have a sunset clause in
there so we can give locals a chance.
Okay. So here's something that I I'd
like to say as far as sunset clauses. A
lot of people are talking about them. Um
there are certain requirements that we
have to do with regard to commerce laws
with and that we can do. And so we would
love for it to be uh New Mexico
companies, New Mexico, you know, people
and individuals who live in New Mexico.
The language behind that is very tricky.
So what I would request for the next
meeting um is that uh people come with
some language with regard to what they
would like the sunset clause. And so,
for example, in some cases, again, this
is different things that we've heard um
in different ways is that it should only
be New Mexico companies that do this.
How do you prove that it's a New Mexico
company? What does that mean? You know,
they do have to have business license in
New Mexico. They have to be registered
with Secretary of State, all of those
sort of things. But other companies can
do that as well. So, how do you actually
define that? How do you actually ensure
that that's the case? um you know
because for example you may end up
having someone who is a part owner in a
company who lives in a different state
and then another owner who lives in New
Mexico. How do you divide that on up?
And so thinking about some of those sort
of things in order to be able to do
that. Um and I do know and Estavon I'll
I see your hand up so I'll get to you in
just a moment. You know some people have
said just do what they've done in
Oregon. There have been some problems
with that particular approach as well,
but we want to make sure that yes, if we
can figure out a way for it to be New
Mexico and New Mexico focused, that is
of course what we would prefer as well.
So, Estavan, go ahead.
>> Thank you, Dominic. Uh, in regard to the
sunset clause, the the president from
Oregon was that, you know, being a
sunset clause, it does have a set
expiration date for them. I believe it
was four years after program inception.
um their metric they're using there is
two years of residence, so proof of
residence and additionally at least 51%
ownership of the business applying for
the license. Um I would say that is
beyond a fair requirement. Um and again
the spirit of the requirement is really
what I think is looking to be honored
here. the idea that we give New Mexico
residents uh folks who have been doing
all the ground work here to kind of help
build and develop this program a fair
and equitable chance to access uh the
supply chain.
>> Thank you for that. We also have Shane
McDaniel there. Uh Shane begin when
ready.
>> Yeah. So, I just want to clarify um when
we're talking about a permit for
cultivation, for harvesting, for what
was it? Processing and production,
something I can't remember what the four
were up there. Um
packaging.
Would there not just be one permit that
covers all of that or are we going to go
like Colorado and require different
permits for every step of the way even
though it's all going to be done in the
same facility? Right? You don't somebody
doesn't grow it and then hire somebody
else to come in and harvest it and then
hire somebody else to package it. They
It's all done at in the same location.
So requiring three different permits is
probably going to be three different
expenses
that
you know make it more expensive to get
in into the um space.
So, so two things with that Shane is one
uh and this is and the other part is
with regard to that they're just
different aspects and so anybody who is
applying for the permit would be able to
apply for either one or any of those as
James was pointing out you might down
the road it may not happen initially but
down the road where different
cultivators who are harvesting may then
turn around and uh send it elsewhere for
processing and packaging as an example.
Um, these are not and again these can be
changed. This is part of why we bring
them up because these are part of what
has happened and what people have
brought up as different areas with
regard to permitting. But it would be
one permit and organizations would just
apply for those portions which they
think are applicable to them. The other
aspect of it is I would like everybody
to remember the Department of Health is
not going to be having a permit fee. Now
that doesn't mean that some of the other
aspects of this won't have costs such as
certificate of occupancy for that
inspection, those sort of things, but um
the Department of Health as far as this
permitting process is not going to have
a fee in and of itself.
>> Okay. So one other thing then then that
we need to discuss then is if it's going
to be done that way where they you know
do some of it in one place and then move
it over to another place is the
transportation what we're going to have
to require for security or right because
that's going to have to be
>> part of the permit too right just like
it is with with uh cannabis right I
can't
>> be uh transporting cannabis without a
permit right
>> you are correct shame that is the next
step.
Remember everybody, we don't have
everything down yet. If we tried to put
everything in, we would never get
finished. Um, and yes, Eric, you No, no,
no. So, just Yes, you are correct. That
is actually one of the next stages.
>> Uh, we have a hand up there by Brett.
>> Please, Brett, go ahead.
>> Yeah, thanks. Um, just a quick question
because I didn't hear anything on it.
Um, is is there going to be any kind of
cap on the number of permits that are
issued and if so, how is that going to
be determined?
>> Brett, that's a great question and
that's actually a question for this
group and for the board.
>> I I guess then I would just put out
there that I I would not support any any
caps on the on the number of permits be
my position. Um, yeah, haven't seen what
how it went down in the the medical
cannabis side and and all that. Um,
yeah, but that's that's my position.
>> Fantastic. We also have a little comment
in the chat there just
>> Oh, go ahead. Sorry.
Um would we we would probably initially
cap it right Dominic for for the kind of
soft roll out in next year and then
as it as the full program gets rolled
out then that cap would kind of come off
I would assume. Uh what I would say uh
is to be honest and uh sort of to kind
of address that with Brett um is that
yes, you know, when medical cannabis
first started uh there were only a
certain amount of licenses that were um
that were allowed and part of the reason
behind that was actually because of the
quite frankly the difference between
state and federal at that time. While
you on paper that hasn't really changed
from a um
I don't know a cultural standpoint, it
is very different nowadays and there and
one of the things that we were
constantly doing quite frankly under
multiple administrations is the program
medical cannabis program was
consistently requesting to approve
additional licenses and was not given
permission to be able to do that. So, um
I think with my saying that you kind of
know where my thoughts are as far as
caps versus no caps. And there is a
comment from James in the chat that says
no cap. The market demand should manage
that. And um I would say that that is a
very clear and a very good statement and
I'll leave it at that. Um it'll happen
naturally through the market is my
belief. But again, that is actually a
consideration that this group uh would
need to make a determination on. But you
will notice we just didn't mention caps
at all anywhere in this document.
Yeah. And there are uh comments in the
the mark or in the uh chat rather that
pretty much just say that as well. So I
don't know that we need to read it. But
there is one other comment
uh and I'm sorry my screen is really
small.
>> Helen Thomas uh it's he says I will also
research testing requirements before the
next meeting. Most growing substrates
are pure grain with no actual soil
involved in the grow. Hence there will
be uh there may be no need for certain
tests. So that was that was the real uh
that was the one that was separate from
the rest. But uh and there was another
comment there by Shane. Uh spawn is done
with grain, but there are many types of
substrates including soil. I believe
Colorado is limiting substrate to
exclude dung. I disagree with that.
Shane says these are not my opinions.
[laughter]
>> Thank you.
>> And just to let you know, uh Gregory
Evans has their hands up.
>> Okay.
>> Okay. Please go ahead.
kind of a random
maybe not totally random but currently
the regulations on myelium until it
becomes a fruiting body is not something
that's like federally regulated. There
are a few states that don't allow spores
and stuff like that. And then it's kind
of this gray area if we have myceliated
grain, right? Does myceliated grain test
at a potency that we're tracking or will
the state allow that as an independent
unregulated
industry all by itself? And do we start
regulating at the moment we inoculate
bulk substrate or or at the point that
we begin to fruit? and like kind of like
where is there room for like side
industries to exist outside of the
regulatory complex and like where do we
define that line? I hope that makes
sense.
>> Uh that does. Um Greg, we are mostly
concerned at this point with regard to
um medical uh the medical application
and program and cultivation at this
time.
You know, that is something I think we
need to kind of uh
delineate pretty early in this process
though is is
we should probably be using, you know,
and I I could be wrong here, but a whole
brooding body mushroom, no myiliated
biomasses or other products like that.
Um, does anybody have any thoughts on
that?
Am
I wrong? No hands up. No hands up.
>> Who else agrees that we should have full
mushroom fruing body only and not my
siliated products?
>> Uh Alan Thomas says I agree. We have a
hands up there by James Ferrer. Um James
do go ahead.
>> I was just going to say what about
truffles?
But uh but actually there was another
one. I think it was Evan asked a
question there on on the delineation of
different types. So you may just want to
do liquid culture and supply everybody
in the state with liquid culture and
that might be you know one one business
that's doing that and so I can see how
you could have a lot of different levels
here in the cultivation process.
We have a comment as well in the chat
just to bring up by Estan. Per um New
Mexico Supreme Court president unh
harvest mushroom/ substrate are not
considered a violation of drug
trafficking laws as they are inadequate
um natural state of mushroom
mushroomness lol [snorts]
considered not inadequate. That's
>> yeah autocorrect is not our friend.
[laughter]
Okay.
Okay. And so, um, just at this point,
um, uh, again, if if anybody had missed
it, we're going to be requesting this
document be put up as soon as possible.
What we will do once it is up is we will
send a message to the people who are
here on this meeting um, so that you are
aware that it is up on the website.
Please give a couple of business days uh
because it does take a little bit of
time for us to be able to get this
through um our IT tickets for them to be
able to post. So, thank you everybody
and then I look forward to those
conversations in the next meeting.
So, all right, Chris, back to you. Um
and uh just to I will bring up the
agenda again just so you have that as
well.
>> I don't think I need the agenda up. Um,
okay. Next thing I wanted to to bring
reading through the mushroom good
agricultural practices. I'm going to
drop the USDA link in the chat right
now.
Um
and um [clears throat]
you know I I think
the intent is to not overregulate and
make these you know a requirement. Um,
but I also think, you know, we we could
use this as a recommendation for
growers. Um, and my intention is to kind
of in the next meeting on the 30th to
kind of get into the weeds on anything
else that we need to with cultivation
and kind of start the conversation
around testing. Um,
and then, you know, we'll we'll kind of
keep working it that way just popping
down the line. So, um, if you all know
testing facilities that, um,
would like to come to that next meeting,
please invite them. I'm going to try to
get some people from Colorado to join
the discussion. And, uh, I'll see if I
can get Tori uh, to come and give us an
update on our um, the lessons learned
from Oregon. Um, I feel really bad that
she wasn't able to speak today. I know
she kind of rushed together to put
something together for us and and that's
kind of a bummer, but I'll see if we can
get her back uh to talk with us. Um
so that's kind of my plan for now.
Uh
are there any other are there any
questions about that or any thoughts
about that plan?
Is there a better standard? I know I've
asked this before. Is there a better
standard than the the mushroom good
agricultural practices that we should be
using or or looking at to kind of guide
this?
>> Okay,
>> we do have a comment in the chat there
by James uh Serbe. Do we have a
scheduled date for the next meeting?
Yeah. So, the next meeting is going to
be on the 30th
at 3:00,
followed by the meeting after that'll be
on the 4th at 3:00. And the last meeting
I have scheduled is on the 11th at 3:00.
And I wanted to start doing some of
these in person, but Department of
Health has requested that I hold off and
we do those virtually during the
legislative session. But I still do want
to um get people face to face and having
some of these discussions. So soon as
legislation legis legislative sessions
are over, I will um get something
scheduled so we can meeting face to
face.
>> Greg, do you have a question?
>> I do. I'm going to take some time and uh
read these practices that you sent and I
think we may need to redline some of
these but in general I think that
they're good starting point. Um,
[clears throat]
one thing that we may end up facing is
the kind of a parody a seed sale parody
for um
that from cannabis. Like are we going to
be requiring that when we start a batch
that it is fracted until the point of
sale and use?
Have we talked about that yet?
We have not yet talked about that
tracking.
>> Yeah, I think
>> you're very quiet. Thank you. I
appreciate that. Thank
>> I think that's going to be a big piece
that we need to to grab in the the
cultivation piece, right? Um,
Brett is asking if there's anything in
particular we should be prepared to go
over at the next meeting. I would say if
you have a vested interest in that
sunset clause, I would really like to
get some language pinned down on that.
That is one of the things that I want to
propose like first off is this is for
New Mexicans. How do we get it for New
Mexicans? Um, so if you could if uh
people want to draft language on that.
Um, the next one would be batch
language. If you want to bring something
to the table about what batches look
like, how they need to be homogenized,
what would make it fair for across the
board, um, we can brainstorm on that and
bring different ideas to the table. Um,
that would be great. Um, but I think
working off of that same document is
probably
prudent. we'll just kind of keep going
with that and nothing is finalized on
there. So, if you're looking it over and
you say, "Hey, you know, we want
something different, bring it to the
table. Let's let's keep working that
language and making sure that we're
getting what we want on that." Shane, do
you have a question? Go ahead.
>> Yeah. So, when you say for New Mexicans,
you're talking about just those people
that are going to be cultivating or or
practitioners. We're not talking about u
potential patients.
Right.
>> Yes. I I think people can definitely
come from out of states to uh get
treatment here. I I'm more talking
about, you know, uh the cultivators, the
labs for testing. Um I would like to see
them uh New Mexicans get a fair shake at
that too. and um
any other process along the way that we
can if we can keep keep our New Mexican
New Mexican residents employed through
this program as much as possible that
that would be my goal with that.
>> Uh we have one comment in the chat by
Brett Phelps. If we submit items to do
via email, will those be distributed uh
to the committee for review?
Um, as far as I know, so we're still
kind of working out the workflow, but
yes, as far as I know, if you submit do
the to the medical psilocybin at
dooh.nm.gov
and make sure that the propagation
committee is uh put in the subject line
that those will get forwarded to me. Is
that correct, Dominic?
>> So, so here's the situation is it
depends on what you're submitting. If
you're trying to submit large documents,
send us links if it's especially if it
is something online and then we will
include that within the minutes or the
meeting records whether it's in this one
or for the next meeting depends on when
it's submitted. Um but uh the biggest
issue that we're really having is
remember we have to do things
transparently and here. So it can also
be something where if you say hey I
would like for this to be reviewed we
can bring it in and we can include it in
the minute records for this meeting as
long as we get them by oh and let me
actually I do have a slide for that as
long as we get that by uh the end of day
tomorrow so that we can include it in if
it's after that it can go into the next
meeting records um but please don't send
us for example we had in some other
groups we had where we were getting
hundred hundreds of pages of documents
that actually were things like the
Oregon regulations where what it really
should be is it should be specific and
saying look at this section and for
example in regulations if it's another
state this section of the regulations
otherwise what ends up happening is
everybody gets overwhelmed with just
getting a ton of information and it
becomes very difficult for people to be
par be able to parse through it
especially because you know the these
meetings are happening relatively
quickly
And so when there's hundreds of pages,
it can be very difficult. And then you
find out it really was just one piece
that somebody was trying to get across.
So be very specific with what you're
submitting. If it's to an already
published document, send us the link.
Send us, you know, where in that link
somebody should go, like if it's on page
two, the third paragraph, that kind of
information. And then we will again,
we'll include it in the records. we do
have to do it this way so that again
we're making sure that all of the
information is available publicly to
everybody. I hope that makes sense.
>> And also I believe you can just bring it
to this committee meeting and we can
allow people to share things as they
raise their hands. Is that correct
Dominic?
>> Yes, exactly.
So we can give you presenter authority
and you can just pop it up on the the
screen and then it'll be recorded as
part of the record and we can all
discuss it in council. So
>> just a quick one here we have from
Gregory Evans regarding meeting
schedule. Are we targeting the 2nd of
February meeting to have our official
first draft for submission?
Yes, that'll be what we're targeting for
our first group of proposals. And it
doesn't need to be a finished product.
The board is going to go and take them
and they'll start picking it up picking
it apart or or looking at it and I'm
sure they'll have recommendations for us
to go back and review and questions for
us to answer and all that type of stuff.
So, um, yeah, we want our first draft to
go out on the or after the the meeting
on the 11.
>> And just to hype everyone up, we have
Kir Evans. Here we go.
>> Yes.
[laughter]
>> Right.
>> Okay. Are there any other proposals that
people would like um to kind of throw
out on the table for consideration
before um we close this up um for the
day? Um that way people can kind of sit
on it for the next meeting.
All right.
Is there any other business that anybody
wants to bring up then?
So, I just want to express a ton of
gratitude for all of you that are coming
and participating. Um, this is, you
know, all of our work collectively is
going to make this program, you know, as
good as we can get it. And so, I'm just
very grateful for all of you that are
coming. And uh I will close this meeting
up a little bit early if there's nothing
else. And I'm looking forward to looking
uh talking with you all next Friday on
the 30th.
>> Thank you everybody.
Gratitude.